Finding Aid for Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) Records, 1919-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) records 1919-[ongoing] 1963-1995
University of Michigan. Center for the Education of Women.
8740 Bimu C484 2
Minutes, correspondence, audiovisual materials, and other records documenting the founding, public programs, research projects, day-to-day administrative activities, and individual staff members of the University of Michigan's Center for the Education of Women.
42 linear feet in 43 boxes
1 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor # 6885 ) has been received in several accessions, beginning in 1983.
The Center for Education of Women records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Center for Education of Women record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 42-43
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 42-43
In the course of processing, the decision was made to restrict access to various files that contained sensitive personal information, most notably and predominantly Social Security Numbers and student academic records. These files were removed from the main run of records. See the access restrictions page for information on the type and length of restrictions on the materials.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Designed to serve the needs of women students as well as women returning to school or work, CEW (then known as the Center for the Continuing Education of Women) was founded with a three part mission of service, advocacy, and research. CEW maintains that mission today, serving University students, staff and faculty, community members, women and men, facing educational, employment or other life issues.
Over the years, CEW has served as a model for other centers, has worked on behalf of women on this campus, in the state of Michigan, and nationally, and has conducted research informing us about women's lives - their work, their education, their family demands, and their aspirations.1
In August 1962, Louise Gilbert Cain prepared "A Memo and Suggestion on the Continuing Education of Women." Mrs. Cain, who worked in the University Extension Service, had become increasing aware of the problems faced by women students when they attempted to re-enter the university. The university responded to Louise Cain's memo by appointing her Special Assistant to Roger W. Heynes, the Vice President for Academic Affairs. Mrs. Cain prepared "Recommendations for a Center for the Continuing Education of Women" in June 1963. An advisory committee of deans was constituted and by May of the following year a proposal for a center had been written.
The Center for the Continuing Education of Women (CEW) began operations on September 1, 1964. It was initially funded by a $15,000 appropriation from President Harlan Hatcher. The second year's operating budget was doubled with the addition of funds from the Alumnae Council.
Louise Cain was appointed director (on leave) of CEW for 1964/65; Jean Campbell was acting director and Helen Hornbeck Tanner was assistant director. Jean Campbell became director in September 1965 and continued in that position until 1985. Subsequent directors have been: Vivian Rogers, 1985-1987; Patricia Wulp, acting director, 1987-1988; and Carol S. Hollenshead, 1988 to the present. After Helen Hornbeck Tanner left CEW in 1967, the Assistant Director position was upgraded to that of Associate Director. CEW Associate Directors have been Patricia Wulp, 1968-1994, and Susan Kaufmann, 1994 to the present.
Throughout the 1960s the center expanded its services to women. The center began publication of a newsletter in the Fall of 1968 and the first conference/workshop "Women in Action" was held in 1969. CEW also began the publication of a paperback series related to women and continuing education.
The center, which reports to the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs, provides educational and vocational guidance to women whose education has been interrupted. The information collected on each counselee or "participant" is coded and the data is used to provide demographic, educational and work experience information on the participant. The data is also used to design CEW programs, to evaluate the center's performance, and to contribute to the basic knowledge about women in today's society. The center organizes discussions, workshops and conferences focusing on women's experiences in higher education and on women's experiences in general. The center's library, a collection of vocational materials and pamphlets of interest to women, provides an additional resource. The center's scholarship program, begun in 1970, the centennial year of women at the University of Michigan, awards merit scholarships. The center also gives emergency grants.
Since its inception the center has become the focus of activities by and for women at the university, lending its support and expertise to the affirmative action movement, the Commission for Women, the development of the Women's Studies Program, and WISE, Women in Science and Engineering. The center's staff has served on university and community committees concerned with women's issues and has brought the perspective of women's needs to university committees. Staff members have worked for changes in university rules and procedures, scheduling and curricula through their membership on such committees as the LS&A Admissions Committee, the Commission on Graduate Requirements, the International Women's Year University of Michigan Committee, the LS&A Commission on Graduation Requirements, and the Committee on the Status of Women in Graduate Education.
The center has also developed programs to benefit special groups of women such as the Arrow Program for undergraduate women, the Evening Program courses (originally designed for student wives), and various programs for international women. In addition, several task forces, such as the Compensation Program and Dependent Care Task Forces, have been developed over the years to address varying needs in the community. More detailed information about the center's history and it's current events and programs can be found on its website at http://www.umich.edu/~cew.
Note to the researcher: The name of the center was changed in 1989 from the Center for the Continuing Education of Women to the Center for the Education of Women.
Directors of the CEW
1964 Louise Cain (in absentia)
1964-1985 Jean Campbell
1985 Patricia Wulp (acting)
1985-1987 Vivian Rogers
1987-1988 Patricia Wulp (acting)
1988-present Carol Hollenshead
_________________
1 From the introduction to the history of CEW on the Center's website at http://www.umich.edu/~cew/aboutcew/hist.htm; a more detailed history of CEW is available in pdf form at http://www.umich.edu/~cew/PDFs/pubs/History%20Section%20Fall%2004.pdf.
The Center for Education of Women collection consist of minutes, correspondence, audiovisual materials, and other records documenting the founding, public programs, research projects, day-to-day administrative activities, and individual staff members of the University of Michigan's Center for the Education of Women. It is divided into four broad subgroups: Central Office Files, 1961-1998; Individual Staff Files, 1919-1999; Audiovisual Materials, 1963-1997; and Restricted Files, 1964-1995. The current CEW collection is the result of a major reprocessing project that combined several new accessions with the pre-existing record group--itself the accumulation of several accessions--and which has resulted in a re-figured collection nearly double the size of the original. The first three subgroups and their major series have been retained, but some of the lower-level organization has been updated to reflect the fuller picture of the Center that the combined set of materials affords.
Documents within folders may be arranged either chronologically or reverse chronologically, based on the existing arrangement of the majority of materials (in both the pre-existing collection and in the new accessions). Also, some files (e.g. most correspondence) were filed by calendar year (Jan-Dec.), while others (notably budgets, staff meetings, and program files) were filed by fiscal year. Unless otherwise noted, files arranged by academic year (indicated in the box list by dates such as '1990/91') run from July of the first year through June of the second year.
Researchers examining the CEW collection may also be interested in related files in the following other Bentley University of Michigan record groups: Institute on Gerontology, Michigan Initiative on Women's Health, Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs.
Additionally, researchers should note the following overlaps between the 'Topical' series in the 'Central Office Files' subgroup and the files of CEW staff members in the 'Individual Staff Files' subgroup:
Counseling: Myra Fabian, Dorothy McGuigan, Vivian Rogers, and Patricia Wulp
Evening Program (especially 1982 and later): Patricia Wulp
Group Counseling and Workshops (e.g. Career Decision Making, Assertiveness, the Step Before the Job Search, etc.): Myra Fabian, Barbara Anton, and Patricia Wulp
Programs by Academic Year: Patricia Wulp
Publicity: Louise Cain, Patricia Wulp and Dorothy McGuigan
Research (including non-traditional student surveys, Women in Science (and Engineering) studies, participant data, and especially Ford Grants): Jean Campbell, Carol Hollenshead, Jean Manis, Hazel Markus, and Dorothy McGuigan
Sexual Harassment Implementation Team and other Sexual Harassment materials: Sue Kaufmann
Women's Initiative Group (WING): Myra Fabian, Sue Kaufmann, Vivian Rogers, and Patricia Wulp
Due to the decentralized nature of the CEW records, researchers are encouraged to check for headings in each of the subgroups and series, even for subjects not listed above.
Acronyms used frequently in the records ad in this finding aid include:
CFW / COW -- UM Commission for Women (prior to 1972, the name was the Commission on Women)
CURIES -- Cross-University Research in Engineering and Science
GEO -- UM Graduate Employees' Organization
IOG -- Institute of Gerontology (Joint UM/Wayne State program)
LSA / LS&A -- UM College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
MAWDAC -- Michigan Association of Women Deans, Administrators and Counselors
MSA -- Michigan Student Assembly (UM student government)
NAWDAC -- National Association of Women Deans, Administrators and Counselors
NACME -- National Action Council for Minorities in Engineering
NSF -- National Science Foundation
OVPR -- UM Office of the Vice President for Research
UM -- University of Michigan (Ann Arbor campus unless otherwise noted)
WING -- UM Women's Initiative Group
WIS / WISE -- Women in Science / Women in Science and Engineering, originally a CEW project that later spun off into its own unit)
Subjects:
Adult education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College publications.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Rogers, Vivian.; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; University of Michigan. Center for the Education of Women.; University of Michigan--Congresses.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cain, Louise G.; Campbell, Jean.; McGuigan, Dorothy Gies.; Wulp, Patricia.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Center for the Education of Women.; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women.; Women--Education.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Central Office Files 1961-1998
  The Central Office Files, 1961-1998 (18.5 linear feet) subgroup contains two series, Core Administration, 1961-1994 and Topical Files, 1962-1998.
  - Core Administrative Records 1961-1994
    The Core Administrative Records, particularly the Staff Meeting, Correspondence, and Review files, are quite valuable in documenting the day-to-day activities of the center and its major programs. In addition, the series includes records regarding the center's creation (including Louise Cain's original proposals and the Alumnae Council's early involvement in the center), annual and long-term reports, CEW descriptions and organizational charts, planning and budget materials, thank-you letters from former participants, and Executive Committee records.
    The researcher should note that the Correspondence sub-series and its components--Directors Correspondence, Staff Correspondence, and Intra-University Correspondence--should not be viewed as complete runs of all incoming or outgoing correspondence. Also, it contains major overlaps both between those three components, with the Topical Files, and with individual staff members' files. This sub-series is largely based on the organization of the pre-existing collection, and does not necessarily reflect how the files came from CEW. Correspondence in the newer accessions were generally kept with either individual staff members' files or with the Topical files. The Intra-University Correspondence is only loosely based on the UM office or unit in question; in some cases it is more topically arranged. (E.g. 'Affirmative Action' contains not only correspondence from the Affirmative Action Program, but also correspondence relating to affirmative action from the President's Office and the VP for Academic Affairs.) Titles of purely topical files of Intra-University Correspondence (with no basis in the university office/administrative unit structure) are enclosed in quote marks ("").
    Similarly, the researcher should be aware that the Staff Meetings and Notes sub-series was compiled from several different staff-members overlapping, partial runs of minutes and notes. Duplicates that had annotations were generally retained. Of special note within the sub-series are the two binders: The first, the 'Staff Calendar and Events' binder includes not only agendas, notes, and calendars (like the regular staff meeting files), but also flyers for CEW events. The second is 'Patricia Wulp's Staff Meetings and Notes binder'. This file, along with the 'Administration Binder' in Wulp's individual staff files, appears to have been started in 1973, while Wulp was serving as Acting Director during a sabbatical of Jean Campbell's. They include staff minutes agendas, calendars, and minutes, as well as Wulp's notes on CEW administration, program planning materials, and correspondence with Jean Campbell and others.
    Finally, many of the materials relating to CEW's budget have been removed from the Core Administrative series and restricted. Other places to find budgetary information include the Planning sub-series (especially for 1985-1987), the Staff Meetings and Notes, and the Correspondence files (especially with the President's office and the Vice President for Academic Affairs). Additionally, records documenting the center's founding and start-up funds, as well as some of its early fundraising efforts can be found in the Alumnae Council section of the Founding and Historical Documents sub-series, and budget information for various CEW programs can be found in the Topical and Individual Staff files under "Programs" and under the names of specific events.
    - Annual and Multi-Year Reports 1965-1994
      - Annual and Partial-Year Reports Submitted to Executive Committee 1965-1968 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Reports on CEW Activities 1971-1976 (Box 1)
      - The University of Michigan Center for Continuing Education of Women, 1964-1977 A Report (Box 1)
      - The University of Michigan Center for Continuing Education of Women, 1964-1984 A Report (Box 1)
      - The University of Michigan Center for Continuing Education of Women 1986-1987 Annual Report (Box 1)
      - Background Material for 1964-1977 Report (Box 1)
      - Updates and Supplements to 1964-1977 Report, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence and Background Regarding 1986-1987 Annual Report (Box 1)
      - Background Material for a Ten-Year Report, circa 1994 (Box 1)
    - Budgets
      - Annual Budget Summaries Binder, 1964/1965-1980/1981 (Box 42)
        [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2056 ]
      - Annual Budget Supporting Detail, (Including Budget Committee materials), 1964/1965-1987/1988 1993-1994, 19 folders (Box 42)
        [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2069 ]
      - Correspondence with President and Vice-President (on Financial Matters) 1974-1983, 2 folders (Box 42)
        [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2058 ]
      - Special Budgets
        - Capital Campaign 1964-1967 (Box 42)
          [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2042 ]
        - Ford Foundation Grant Budgets 1976-1980 (Box 42)
          [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2055 ]
        - Priority Funds 1975-1981 (Box 42)
    - CEW Committees 1962-1990
      - Advisory Committee 1962-1964 (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee
        - Correspondence 1964-1975, 1978-1990, 5 folders (Box 1)
        - Meetings 1964-1989, 8 folders (Box 1)
        - Membership 1964-1989 (Box 1)
        - Notes and Supporting Information 1965-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Research Advisory Committee 1977, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1963-1993
      - Directors Correspondence 1967-1980, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Directors Correspondence 1981-1988, 1991, 9 folders (Box 2)
      - Staff Correspondence 1972-1993, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Intra-University Correspondence
        - Admissions 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        - Affirmative Action 1969-1986 (Box 2)
        - Bureau of Psychological Services 1963-1970 (Box 2)
        - Bureau of School Services 1969-1971 (Box 2)
        - Career Planning and Placement 1968-1973 (Box 2)
        - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT) 1965-1967 (Box 2)
        - Commission for Women 1973 (Box 2)
        - Community College Advisory Committee 1973-1974 (Box 2)
        - Dearborn Campus 1971-1973 (Box 2)
        - Development 1963-1973 (Box 2)
        - Education, School of 1970-1972 (Box 2)
        - Financial Aids 1964-1974 (Box 2)
        - Flint Campus 1971-1973 (Box 2)
        - "Friends" 1969-1972 (Box 2)
        - Graduate School 1971-1973 (Box 2)
        - Higher Education 1971-1973 (Box 2)
        - History Department 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        - "Honorary Degrees" 1969-1973 (Box 2)
        - Law School 1972 (Box 2)
        - Library Science, School of 1971 (Box 2)
        - Literature, Science, and the Arts (LS&A) 1969-1973 (Box 3)
        - Medical Center 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - Michigan Women in Science 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - "Miscellaneous" 1968-1972 (Box 3)
        - Mortar Board 1965-1972 (Box 3)
        - Nursing School 1968-1972 (Box 3)
        - Physics Department 1964-1969 (Box 3)
        - Physical Education 1968-1973 (Box 3)
        - President's Office 1964-1988 (Box 3)
        - Psychology Department 1971-1973 (Box 3)
        - Public Health, School of 1971-1973 (Box 3)
        - Regents 1963-1973 (Box 3)
        - Registrar 1967-1974 (Box 3)
        - Scheduling Office 1969-1972 (Box 3)
        - Social Work, School of 1971-1973 (Box 3)
        - Sociology Department 1965, undated (Box 3)
        - Vice President (VP) for Academic Affairs
          - General 1966-1988, 4 folders (Box 3)
          - Mary Ann Swain 1983-1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - VP and CFO 1970-1971 (Box 3)
        - VP for Development and University Relations 1972-1983 (Box 3)
        - VP for Information Technology 1985-1986 (Box 3)
        - VP for Research 1978-1986 (Box 3)
        - VP for State Relations 1970, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
        - VP for Student Services 1969, 1979-1984 (Box 3)
        - Women's Studies 1972-1978 (Box 3)
    - Founding and Historical Documents 1961-1990
      - Alumnae Council Materials
        - CEW Committee
          - Correspondence (A. Myers) 1962-1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Correspondence (General) 1964-1966 (Box 3)
          - Updates and Reports 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Topical
          - Donor Plaque 1966-1967 (Box 3)
          - Extension 1961-1962 (Box 3)
          - Miscellaneous 1962-1967 (Box 3)
          - Publicity 1964-1966 (Box 3)
      - CEW Histories and Historical Information, circa 1966-1980 (Box 3)
      - "History Volume II", circa 1980-1990 (Box 3)
        (binder originally had note indicating volume I still at CEW)
      - Proposals for CEW 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    - Organization and Description 1970-1987
      - Descriptions 1970-1979 (Box 3)
      - Organization Charts 1972-1987 (Box 3)
    - Planning 1970-1994
      - Goals 1970-1974 (Box 3)
      - Program and Budget Planning 1978-1980, 1 folders (Box 3)
      - Program and Budget Planning 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Vivian Rogers' Planning Binder (including budget and goals planning, staff meetings and notes, annual report preparation, and background documents from 1985-1986) 1985-1987 (Box 4)
      - Strategic Development Plan 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Reviews 1973-1983
      - Background Material used in 1975 Assessment Process, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
      - Evaluation and Planning Project 1975-1977 (Box 4)
      - 1982 Review: Final Report and Follow Up, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - 1982 Review: Precursors, Background, and Preparation: 1980-1982 (Box 4)
    - Staff Meetings and Notes 1965-1993
      - 1965/1966-December 1975, 12 folders (Box 4)
        (missing Winter term 1973 also see Patricia Wulp's Staff Meeting and Notes Binder)
      - January 1976-1985/86, 20 folders (Box 5)
      - 1986/87-1992/1993, 11 folders (Box 6)
      - "Staff Calendar and Events" (Binder) November 1988-December 1989 (Box 6)
      - Patricia Wulp's Staff Meeting and Notes Binder circa 1973-1977 (Box 6)
    - Thank You Letters 1970-1992, undated, 24 folders (Box 6)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical files are arranged alphabetically and contain material about specific conferences and events sponsored by the center, the research it has conducted, its liaisons with and involvement in other groups working on similar portfolios, and its day-to-day activities. In the original collection, the topical files of each accession were formed around director Jean Campbell's topical files, with the additions of similar topical files from associate director Pat Wulp and office files that were the work of several staff members. These earlier runs of topical files--all of which covered essentially the same date range--have been combined into a single series, into which similar material from the newer accessions have been added.